(gentle music)
- [Narrator] At exactly 8:32
AM on a sunny morning in 2001,
President Bush leaves his room
at the Colony Beach Resort
in Florida and gets into
his Presidential limousine,
heading to a local elementary school.
The reason for this visit
is that he's promoting
a new education program.
On the scale of priority,
this is the kind of event
that would be forgotten by history.
However, just minutes before
Bush arrives at the school,
a breaking news message makes the rounds,
one that will forever change
the course of history.
At 8:46 AM, Flight 11 crashes
into the North Tower of
the World Trade Center.
And the news of this event
spreads in a, until then,
historically unprecedented manner.
Just one minute and 28
seconds after the impact,
a camera crew from WNYW goes on air.
- [Reporter] Jim, just a few moments ago,
something believed to be a plane,
crashed into the South Tower
of the World Trade Center.
- [Narrator] At 8:49 AM,
CNN pauses their programming
to cover the crash,
followed by CNBC, ABC, NBC,
CBS, Fox News
and international television stations.
In less than 10 minutes,
the eyes of the whole world
were focused on New York City.
However, nothing is known about the causes
at this point in time,
and speculation about a possible accident
is circulating in Sarasota,
where Bush is preparing
to head into the school.
Right along Bush's side,
is White House Press
Secretary Ari Fleischer,
who throughout the day is
taking handwritten notes
that reveal how everything unfolded
from the President's perspective,
with White House Chief of Staff Karl Rove
informing the President about the impact
just before he heads into
the school for the event.
As the nation listens to TV anchors
speculating potential
reasons for the crash,
the President listens to school
children reading stories.
There's still the possibility
that it could all be
just a tragic accident.
But a few minutes later, this
possibility can be ruled out.
At 9:03 AM, United Flight 175
heads for the South Tower.
Exactly two minutes elapsed
as the news circulated among reporters
and White House staff,
with the President being
one of the few people
unaware of what's going
on until eventually,
the White House Chief of
Staff leans into Bush's ear
and says, "A second plane
hit the second tower.
America is under attack."
A few miles away, at this time,
a US government modified Boeing 747
with the usual call sign, Air Force One,
prepares to take the President
back on a short journey
to Washington DC.
What no one can predict at this point
is that the President
will be on that plane
for much longer today.
After the school event was cut short,
senior White House staff gathers
in an adjoining classroom
for a briefing, following the news on TV,
much like the rest of the country,
and an initial statement was prepared.
- Today we've had a national tragedy.
- [Narrator] Simultaneously,
the Air Force is clearing the way
for a seamless flight of
the Presidential plane.
- [Air Base Staff] I need
you guys to keep a good eye
on Air Force One today and make
sure that it gets priority.
They're gonna probably
be taking off early here
to come back to Washington D.C.
So is there any way that
you can help us out on that?
- [Command Center Staff] Yeah.
- [Air Base Staff] They're out of Sarasota
and they'll be coming back
probably in the next hour,
I believe.
- [Narrator] But whether
Bush should really return
to the capital in this
situation is unclear,
as the attacks on the nation continue.
While the President is in his limousine
heading to the airport, he's
informed of yet another strike.
- [News Anchor] This is
coming at 9:43 Eastern time.
We're looking at a live
picture from Washington
and there is smoke pouring
out of the Pentagon.
- [Narrator] About 10
minutes after the strike
against the Pentagon,
Air Force One is about to
take off from Sarasota.
The Secret Service had received reports
that a person with an unclear device
was near one end of the runway,
and the fear was that
it might be a weapon.
Even though later, it turned
out to be nothing but a camera.
As a precaution, the pilot
decided to turn the plane around
and take off from the other side
so as not to be in the line of
sight of a possible shooter.
Unlike usual,
the plane also climbs at
an extremely steep angle,
a safety maneuver that can
protect against ground attacks.
As Air Force One
continues to gain altitude
heading towards the capital city,
one other plane over US airspace
is still under the
control of the hijackers.
Flight 93, initially
heading to San Francisco,
had changed course.
Now, also approaching Washington DC.
As it later turns out, the
passengers of this flight
had heard of the attacks on New York
and initiated a revolt
against the hijackers,
with passengers attempting
to gain control.
At 10:03 AM, Flight 93 crashes
in a field in Pennsylvania.
Although the revolt was unsuccessful
in saving the passengers,
it did save lives by
preventing the hijackers
from reaching their destination.
Meanwhile, aboard Air Force One,
heated debates are raging
about where the President
should be flying at this time.
Bush himself had given the
order to return to Washington.
But in the midst of an ongoing threat,
the Secret Service was
not about to risk it.
Bush was barred, or at
least strongly discouraged
from returning to DC.
Instead, Barksdale Air Force
Base in Louisiana was chosen.
Here, Air Force One can then refuel,
and a longer plan can be
devised for where the President
can most effectively carry out his duties.
As the plane heads for Louisiana,
growing concerns are also
raised about the possibility
of Air Force One itself becoming a target.
While the plane is equipped
with flares and smoke screens
to detect radar and heat-guided missiles,
it has no way to protect itself
against an airliner collision.
- [Herndon Center Staff] Air Force One
is filing a random route, by the way.
- [FAA Staff] Okay.
- [Herndon Center Staff] We
don't know where they decided
to go, but they still don't
have a fighter escort.
- [FAA Staff] They still do not?
- [Herndon Center Staff] That's correct.
- [FAA Staff] Holy cow.
- [Narrator] Adding to this concern
is the fact that some airplane
were not immediately
responding to ATC calls,
which led to the wrong belief
that there might be an
additional free aircraft
still missing.
Every plane in the sky was
seen as a possible threat now,
therefore Air Force One started climbing
to an extremely high flight level,
above the usual cruising
altitude for commercial flights
heading up to 45,000 feet,
so they can outrun anybody.
While lateral movement is
more difficult to track,
Air Force One had this
altitude for itself.
And then, towards the end of
their flight to Louisiana,
Air Force One was joined
by two fighter jets
that had taken off from
Joint Reserve Base Ellington
to escort the President
for the final few minutes.
Throughout the flight,
Air Force One's normally
stable telephone lines
were suddenly unreliable,
making communications
with the White House,
where Vice President Cheney
was sheltered in a secret
bunker, very difficult.
Communication networks across the country
were at their limit that day.
And Air Force One wasn't an exception.
And it was during this flight
when a controversial
military order was made,
one that until today,
is a controversial topic of discussion.
In the bunker below the White House,
there were ongoing fears
that another hijacked plane
was flying towards Washington DC.
It later turned out
that this was Flight 93,
which crashed in Pennsylvania
10 minutes earlier.
However, the information about the crash
had not yet reached the White House.
And between 10:12 and 10:18 AM,
Vice President Cheney was asked
whether this plane should be shot down
if it continued to head
towards the capital.
According to witnesses, as
well as Cheney's own biography,
he replied without hesitation
and gave the go ahead
for the shooting down
of a commercial plane that poses danger.
The problem with such an order, however,
is that Cheney, as Vice President,
is not part of the
military chain of command.
According to this hierarchy,
such an order comes from the President,
with the only other person in question
being the Secretary of
Defense, Donald Rumsfeld,
who is second in line to the President.
Rumsfeld could not be reached,
because he was at the Pentagon,
which was itself the target of an attack,
and he was busy helping
with rescue work on-site.
Standing in the same
secure room as Dick Cheney
when he made that order,
was White House Deputy Chief
of Staff Joshua Bolten.
After Cheney made the order,
he immediately asked Cheney
to call the President
to confirm this command.
Cheney does exactly so,
and rings Air Force One at 10:18 AM
to speak with the President.
According to the investigation report,
this phone call lasts two minutes,
which lines up with the notes
that Ari Fleischer took at 10:20 AM.
These notes show the words,
"authorized shot down if necessary."
The question, however, remains.
Did Vice President Cheney
initially give a command
that he wasn't entitled to give?
He himself denied it,
and stated that he had
already confirmed this order
in a previous conversation with Bush.
And in fact, Fleischer's notes
do show that Bush and Cheney
spoke on the phone beforehand,
visible in the above entry at 9:45 AM.
However, there is no
sign of a conversation
about a possible shootdown.
Whether the two spoke about this or not
can not be answered conclusively.
Upon landing at Barksdale Air Force Base,
a more detailed briefing took place,
and the President once
again addressed the nation.
- Freedom itself was
attacked this morning.
- [Narrator] As Bush delivers his speech,
his security team and national advisors
have come up with a new destination.
The President is determined
to head to the White House,
saying, "I want to go back home, ASAP.
And I don't want whoever this is,
holding me outside Washington."
But the Secret Service
disagrees, with Eddie Marinzel,
the President's lead Secret
Service agent, saying,
"Our people are saying
it's too unsteady still."
Therefore, at 1:48 PM,
Air Force One takes off
from Barksdale Base,
heading not for Washington,
but for the Offut Air
Force Base in Nebraska.
The reason they decided to go here
is that this base has
the US STRATCOM bunker,
an immensely protected
underground compound
with advanced communication capabilities.
On this journey to Nebraska,
Air Force One was flying
almost entirely alone
in American airspace.
Already at 9:45 AM, one
hour after the first strike,
a complete closure of all
US airspace was ordered,
after which aircraft had to land
at the nearest possible airport.
At around 12:15, this
closure was completed,
with all commercial and
general aviation grounded.
After landing at Offut Air Force Base,
the President and his team gathered
in the US STRATCOM bunker.
It is located 40 feet
underground and is thickly built
to provide protection
from any possible attacks.
In addition to an extensive
communication center,
there are also several
other rooms with offices
and even bedrooms, so that
this station could function
as an overnight base, if necessary.
At 4:36 PM, the act of
attacks on the nation
seemed to have come to an end,
and the security situation
allows the President
to take his third flight of the day.
Air Force One departs, bound
for Joint Base Andrews.
But even this flight was carried out
under immense security concerns
as the Secret Service not
only worries about security
in the airspace,
but also considers
possible threats on board.
One not frequently reported on concern
was that just a few hours earlier,
a call had come in at the
White House switchboard
with a message that resulted
in the worst of fears.
The message on the call
was "Angel is next."
Angel is the internal code
word for Air Force One,
and what is especially concerning
is the fact that this code
word was not publicly known,
leading Secret Service
agents to suspect an insider
might be plotting an attack on the plane.
In face of this ominous message,
the Secret Service decided
to permanently station agents
in the aisle of the Presidential area.
Additionally,
another agent was placed
near the cockpit door,
ready to defend it from any intruders.
In the later investigation into
the events of September 11,
it'll appear that a number
of misunderstandings
had led to this warning,
and that these exact words
were not uttered on the phone.
It was one of many false alarms that day
that severely raised tensions
aboard Air Force One.
At 6:44 PM, Air Force One lands
at Andrews Air Force Base.
From here,
the President flies on Marine
One to the White House,
where he will address the
nation from the Oval Office
that same evening.
A simple journey that was supposed to take
just two and a half hours,
turned into a tense relay
race between Sarasota, Florida
and the White House in DC.
All in all, it took more than nine hours,
a time period in which
thousands of lives were lost
in an attack that will
shape the next decades.
As for Air Force One,
this was arguably the most serious test
of its safety capabilities
that ever occurred.
Many of the protocols were shown to work
and the pilots made decisions
to ensure maximum safety.
At the same time, the day
also revealed weaknesses
with a large delay until the
flight could be escorted,
as well as confusion due to false reports,
and an unreliable communication network.
All things that were improved
on in the following years.
The September 11 attacks
brought the realities
of global events directly into
our homes through cable news.
In the more than 20 years since,
the media landscape has
changed dramatically.
Today, outlets not only
rely on TV ratings,
but also on generating clicks,
leading to increasingly divisive headlines
and stories designed to provoke outrage.
And it's easy to fall into this cycle
of only reading articles
that confirm our opinions.
To better navigate this, I
personally use Ground News,
the sponsor of this video.
Their app allows you to see
how different news outlets
report on the same story,
helping you spot biases.
For example,
this story about the
Donald Trump criminal case,
which interestingly is almost
exclusively reported on
by right-leaning media.
The story as written up
by right-wing outlets
is that the judge in the trial
against former President Trump
has told the jury that
they do not need to believe
Trump is guilty to convict
him, which if it was true,
would be a scandal.
However, Ground News
also rates the factuality
of these outlets,
and it provides a different
article that clarifies.
What the judge actually said
is that jurors can disagree
on the mechanism of his guilt,
but very well have to be unanimous
on whether guilty or not.
Ground News highlights
these blind spots for you.
That is, when a story is
disproportionately covered
by either left or right-leaning media,
and it lets you compare headlines
to see which spin
different outlets will give
a certain topic,
so you can see every side of
what the political spectrum
is saying about the same story.
Ground News also provides information
on the ownership
structure of news outlets.
Plus you can track your own news bias
based on the articles that you read.
In order to access all
these amazing features,
you can get 40% off their
Vantage subscription
if you use my link, ground.news/neo.
It truly is a fantastic
way to stay informed
without falling into an echo chamber.
So thank you for checking out Ground News,
and thank you so much
for watching this video.